The next portion of model context protocol that we're going to investigate is the client.
The purpose of the client is to provide a means of communication between your server and a MCP
server. This client is going to be your access point to all the tools implemented by that server.
Now MCP is transport agnostic. This is a fancy term that just says that the
client and the server can communicate over a variety of different protocols.
A very common way to run a MCP server right now is on the same physical machine as the MCP client.
And if these two things are running on the same machine then they can communicate over
standard input output. And that's what we are going to be setting up later on inside this section.
There are however other ways we can connect the MCP client with the MCP server. So they can also
connect over HTTP or WebSockets or any of a number of other varieties or techniques.
Once a connection has been formed between the client and the server,
they communicate by exchanging messages. The exact messages that are allowed are all
defined inside of the MCP spec. Some of the message types that you and I are going to be
focusing on are the ListToolsRequest and the ListToolsResult. As you guessed, ListToolsRequest
is sent from the client to the server, and it asks the server to list out all the different
tools that it provides. The server would then respond with a ListToolsResult message,
which contains a list of all the different tools that it can provide.
Two other common message types that you and I are going to see are the CallToolRequest
and CallToolResult. The first will ask the server to run a tool with some particular arguments,
and the second will contain the result of the tool run.
Now at this point in time, we've got this idea of a server and a client,
but I suspect it's probably not really clear how all this stuff really works together.
So here's what we're going to do in the remainder of this video. We are going to walk through
an example call between a lot of different things. So this will be kind of an involved process,
but we're going to imagine the communication that goes on between a user, our server that
we're putting together, a MCP client, a MCP server, GitHub as some provider that we're
trying to access some data from, and Cloud. So let's get to it. Again, step by step.
First thing we would expect to happen is a user to submit some kind of query or question to our
server, like what repositories do I have? At this point, it would be up to our server to make a
request off to Cloud. But in that request, we want to list out all the different tools that Cloud has
access to. So before our server can make the request off to Cloud, it's first going to go
through a little side detour through the MCP client and the server. So here's what happens.
The server is going to realize that it needs to see a list of tools to send off to Cloud,
along with the user's query. So it's going to ask the MCP client to get a list of tools.
The MCP client in turn is going to send a list tools request off to the server,
and the server will respond with a list tools result. Now that our MCP client has a list of
the tools, it will give that list of tools back to the server. And now our server has everything
it needs to make an initial request off to Cloud. It has both the original message from the user
and a list of tools to include. So our server can make a request off to Cloud with that query
and the set of tools. Cloud is going to take a look at the tools and realize, you know what,
in order to answer the user's original question right here, I really want to call a tool. So
Cloud would respond with some tool use message part. At this point, our server is going to realize
that Cloud wants to run a tool, but our server is no longer really in charge of executing any
tools. Instead, our tools are going to be executed by the MCP server. So in order to run the tool
that Cloud is asking for, our server is going to ask the MCP client to run a tool with some
particular arguments that are provided by Cloud. The MCP client, however, doesn't actually run
the tool. It's going to send a call tool request off to the MCP server. The MCP server will receive
that request and make a follow-up request off to GitHub. So this is where we would actually be
getting a list of repositories that belong to this particular user. GitHub would respond with that
list of repositories. Then the MCP server would wrap up that data inside of a call tool result
and send that back to the MCP client. Then the MCP client in turn would hand the result off to
our server. Now our server has the list of repositories and it can make a follow-up request
to Cloud with the tool result parked inside of a user message. So this tool result would include
the list of repositories that Cloud was asking for. And now Cloud has all the information it
needs to formulate a final response. So it'll write out some text of something like your
repositories are and then send that back to our server. And our server would send it on back to
our user. All right, so this flow, yes, it is rather complicated. The reason I want to show
you this is that we are going to see all these different pieces as you and I start to implement
our own custom MCP client and MCP server a little bit later on.